Finding Aid for Department of Psychiatry (University of Michigan) records, 1959-2013
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Department of Psychiatry (University of Michigan) records 1959-2013, 1988-2013
University of Michigan. Department of Psychiatry.
47 GB online
2 linear feet
0360 BImu C46 2
Records of the University of Michigan Department of Psychiatry. The collection contains administrative files and publications. Also includes records and video materials for the Annual Waggoner Lectureship.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Publications are received periodically from the unit (donor no. 647 ) in 1999 and 2014.
Periodic additions to the records expected.
The collection is open without restriction.
The history of mental health care at the University of Michigan goes back to the late 1870s within the Medical School. Its development and that of the Department of Psychiatry evolved in part with William James Herdman's career. Herdman was a faculty member at the university since 1875 that had developed an interest in the new field of psychiatry. He would work to make psychiatric research and teaching a part of the Medical School's curriculum.
When the Medical Department initiated the four-year program in 1890, Herdman was assigned to the new chair of nervous diseases and electrotherapeutics. In 1898, his title changed again to Professor of Diseases of the Mind and Nervous System and Electrotherapeutics. His work in the teaching of these disciplines as well as neurology was key in the university's interest and efforts to establish facilities for research in these areas. Herdman and the Regents of the university worked to get the state legislature's to allocate funding to build a psychopathic hospital. This was to be a research and clinical facility that would serve the university, its medical community and the state of Michigan.
The hospital opened in 1906. Albert M. Barrett, who had succeeded Herdman as Professor of Psychiatry and Disease of the Nervous System, became its first director. Barrett would also oversee psychiatry and neurology within the Department of Nervous and Mental Diseases. This department was the predecessor of what later became the Department of Psychiatry. It was in 1920 that said department was divided into the Department of Neurology and the Department of Psychiatry. The latter would be chaired by Barrett until 1936.
Barret was succeeded in the role of chairman by associate professor of neurology Raymond Walter Waggoner in 1937. During his tenure Waggoner oversaw the completion of the Neuropsychiatric Institute by ensuring funding from the legislature and the university. Waggoner remained chair of the Department of Psychiatry until 1970.
Albert J. Silverman would serve as the next chairman for the department and would hold that title until 1984. John F. Greden, was appointed chair in 1985. Greden was instrumental in the proposal and establishment of the University's Depression Center. In 2007, Gregory Dalack would succeed Greden in chairing the department, first as interim chair and as permanent department chair in 2010.
Department Chairs
1920-1936 Albert M. Barrett
1937-1970 Raymond W. Waggoner
1970-1981 Albert Silverman
1985-2007 John Greden
2007-2010 Gregory Dalack (interim)
2010- Gregory Dalack
The Department of Psychiatry records contain two series, the Raymond W. Waggoner Lectureship series and a Publications series.
The Department of Psychiatry records contains manuscript and digital materials related to the Raymond W. Waggoner Lectureship events, and Department publications.
The Raymond W. Waggoner Lectures series (1.5 linear feet and 47 GB, 1996-2013) contains informational materials, transcripts and video recordings for the Raymond W. Waggoner Lectureship on Ethics and Values in Medicine since its establishment in 1996. Digital video and transcripts can be accessed through links in this finding aid.
The Publications series (0.5 linear feet, 1959 -- 2006) contains unit publications such as annual reports for the late 1980s, informational brochures, bulletins and information on residency programs. Additional materials include information on the Albert J. Silverman Research Conference and a guide to scientific publications produced by the department faculty.
Subjects:
Mental health.; Psychiatry.; Raymond R. Waggoner Lectureship.; University of Michigan. Department of Psychiatry.
Genre Terms:
Bulletins.; Digital moving image formats.; Pamphlets.
- Raymond W. Waggoner Lectures 1996-2013
  The Raymond W. Waggoner Lectures series (1.5 linear feet and 47 GB, 1996-2013) contains informational materials, transcripts and video recordings for the Raymond W. Waggoner Lectureship on Ethics and Values in Medicine since its establishment in 1996. Digital video and transcripts can be accessed through links in this finding aid.
  - About Raymond W. Waggoner (Box 1)
  - Robert Michels Ethics and the Changing Role of the Physician: The Coming Crisis in the Practice of Medicine, 1996
    - Background material (Box 1)
    - Video and transcripts, .ZIP file
  - Alan Stone Physician Assisted Suicide: Where Do We Stand?, 1997
    - Background materials (Box 1)
    - Video and transcripts, .ZIP file
  - Arthur Caplan What is Wrong With Human Cloning?: The Ethics of Technological Reproduction, 1998
    - Background material (Box 1)
    - Video and transcripts, .ZIP file
  - Paul S. Applebaum No Place to Hide: Threats to Confidentiality and Privacy in Medicine, 1999
    - Background materials (Box 1)
    - Video and transcripts, .ZIP file
  - Catherine D. DeAngelis Integrity in Scientific Publications: Implications for Research (no video), 2000
    - Background material (Box 1)
    - Video and transcripts, .ZIP file
  - Harold T. Shapiro Ethical Considerations in Research on Human Subjects-Time for Change ... Again, 2001
    - Background material (Box 1)
    - Video and transcripts, .ZIP file
  - Mary Sue Coleman Care Without Coverage: Too Little, Too Late, 2002
    - Background material (Box 1)
    - Video and transcripts, .ZIP file
  - Leon R. Kass Ageless Bodies, Happy Souls: Biotechnology and the Pursuit of Perfection, 2003
    - Background material (Box 1)
    - Video and transcripts, .ZIP file
  - Sheldon Krimsky Academic Science and Entrepreneurship: Are the Conflicts Reconcilable?, 2004
    - Background material (Box 1)
    - Video and transcripts, .ZIP file
  - Leon Eisenberg When Good Men and Women Do Nothing-Doctors at Abu Ghraib and Guantanamo, 2005
    - Background material (Box 1)
    - Video and transcripts, .ZIP file
  - Howard Markel Contemplating Pandemics: The Role of Historical Inquiry in Developing Pandemic Influenza Mitigation Strategies for the 21st Century, 2006
    - Background material (Box 1)
    - Video and transcripts, .ZIP file
  - Thomas Murray Issues Review Panel, World Anti-Doping Agency: Ethics, Genetics, and the Future of Sport, 2007
    - Background material (Box 2)
    - Video and transcripts, .ZIP file
  - Ezekiel J. Emanuel Beyond Band-Aids: How to Cure America's Sick Healthcare System, 2008
    - Background material (Box 2)
    - Video and transcripts, .ZIP file
  - Lawrence O. Gostin Redressing the Unconscionable Health Gap: A Proposal for a Global Plan for Justice, January 2010
    - Background material (Box 2)
    - Video and transcripts, .ZIP file
  - Bernard Lo Old and New Ethical Problems in Innovative Stem Cell Research, November 2010
    - Background material (Box 2)
    - Video and transcripts, .ZIP file
  - Laura Roberts On Becoming a Physician: Stresses and strengths of physicians-in-training, 2011
    - Background material (Box 2)
    - Video and transcripts, .ZIP file
  - Lazarus, Jeremy A., Fixing Healthcare the Ethical Way 2012
    - Background material (Box 2)
    - Video and transcripts, .ZIP file
  - Sade, Robert, Myths and Misconceptions in Biomedical Ethics 2013
    - Background material (Box 2)
    - Video and transcripts, .ZIP file
- Publications
  The Publications series (0.5 linear feet, 1959 -- 2006) contains unit publications such as annual reports for the late 1980s, informational brochures, bulletins and information on residency programs. Additional materials include information on the Albert J. Silverman Research Conference and a guide to scientific publications produced by the department faculty.
  - Annual Reports (Box 2)
  - Annual Progress Report, 1988-1989, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Annual Report, 1986 (Box 2)
  - Brochures 1970, 2006 (Box 2)
  - Bulletins (Box 2)
  - Department of Psychiatry, 1959 and circa 1976, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Residency Programs in Psychiatry at the University of Michigan Medical Center, c.1966 (Box 2)
  - Programs 1998 (Box 2)
  - Scientific Publications 1993-1994 (Box 2)
  - Sixth Annual Albert J. Silverman Research Conference 1995 (Box 2)
  - Youth --Nominated Support Team Intervention Manual 2001 (Box 2)